Narrator: Part 1
Emma Barnett: If we just go back to the start, it all began when you were in your house,
with your mum, in 1985.
Anthony Ray Hinton: Well, um, that particular morning, like any other morning,
I woke up and had breakfast and went outside and laid on up and the Đ
the day, it got hotter and hotter in Alabama Đ and it was in July andÉ
I goes out and I fire up the old lawnmower,
and about 25 minutes into cutting the grass I just happen to look up,
and there stood two white gentlemen that IŐd never seen before.
I cut the lawnmower off and I said, ÔCan I help you?Ő
and one of Őem replied, ÔYes, weŐre looking for Anthony Ray Hinton.Ő
I said, ÔThat would be me. Again, how can I help you?Ő
and he said, ÔWe are detectives from the Birmingham Police Department.
We have a warrant for your arrest.Ő
And I kept asking the detective, ÔWhy am I being arrested?Ő
They never would reply, and I said, ÔDetective, why are yŐall arresting me?Ő
and he finally turned around and he said, ÔWe gonna charge you with first-degree robbery,
first-degree kidnapping, first-degree attempted murder.Ő
I said, ÔWell, you got the wrong guy. I ainŐt done none of that.Ő
He said, ÔLet me tell you something, right now,
I donŐt care whether you did it or didnŐt do it,
but I want you to know that you gonna be convicted of it.Ő
He said, ÔIŐm gonna make sure of it.Ő
And I got convicted.
The judge proudly stood up that day and said,
ÔAnthony Ray Hinton, you have been found guilty by a jury of your peers,
and itŐs the order of this court that I sentence you to death,
and may God have mercy on your soul.Ő
I had no feelings, I, I just felt numb,
I felt alive but yet dead at the same time.
I kept wondering how a innocent man that was out cutting grass,
how do he go from cutting grass to all of a sudden
his whole world is turned upside down, and now the judge is saying,
ÔI sentence you to death.Ő And I kept saying, ÔHow did I get here?
How am I gonna be killed for something that I didnŐt do?
What did I do so bad in this world that I deserve this?Ő
Emma Barnett:I was gonna say,
how long were you angry for in those first years of prison, then?
Anthony Ray Hinton: Three long years.
I didnŐt speak to another human being for three years.
Every time one of the guards would ask me anything,
IŐd just get a pencil out, or a pen, or whatever I had,
and write my response. I didnŐt wanna talk to nobody.
I was just sitting there feeding off hate.
Emma Barnett:What happened after three years?
Anthony Ray Hinton: Well, after those three yearsÉ
I woke up to the sound of a grown man crying and weeping.
This is a man that I had lived by for three years
and never asked him his name or where he was from.
But, my mother had taught me compassion at a very early age
and she told me that no matter what one does in life, he or she deserved compassion.
And so, that compassion made me, for the first time, er, holler out,
and I said, ÔHey, over there!Ő I said, ÔIs something wrong?Ő
And it took this man a while to reply and finally he replied and he said,
ÔWell, I just got word my mother passed.Ő
And I told him how sorry I was to hear that.
And I told him that if I could do anything, let me know.
I sit back on that little small bed and thatŐs when I thanked God that my mother was still alive,
and I think that was the beginning of me coming back to Đ to human form,
to realize that, although I was in a five-by-seven, I had something to be thankful forÉ
Emma Barnett: You did have a friend, as I understand it,
who came to see you throughout this time.
Anthony Ray Hinton: Oh, you talking Őbout Lester!
Emma Barnett: Yes.
Anthony Ray Hinton: Oh yes, I smile every time I see Lester today.
I talk to Lester every day. Lester came to see me 30 straight years.
Lester came a total of 10,999 visits.
Er, rain, sleet, snow, whatever, Lester always cameÉ
Lester was four and I was six at the time we met each other.
Two little kids that just Đ our mothers told us to go out and play,
and our friendship have lasted for 59 years,
and Lester and I donŐt agree on everything, but Lester and I have a bond that is unbreakable.